Brents Carlton
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Brents Carlton papers
1921-1987
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Brents Carlton
2.0 linear feet
The papers of Brents Carlton (b. 1903) date from 1921 through 1987. The collection consists of 2.0 linear feet of biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, notes, a scrapbook, exhibition files, art work, photographs, and printed material documenting his career as a sculptor.
Biographical Note
Brents Carlton was born October 31, 1903, in Roswell, New Mexico. After a few years, his family moved to Arkansas. In 1923, Carlton moved to San Francisco to attend the California School of Fine Arts for four years. From 1928 to 1929, he studied under a scholarship at the Art Students' League in New York, after which he returned to San Francisco and established his own studio. In order to support his family, Carlton was also employed as a pharmacist for 30 years.
In 1938, Carlton created several of his most notable works, two large cast concrete figures for the Fountain of Western Waters Polynesian Group at the Golden Gate international Exposition and two eighteen-foot figures for the façade of the California State Building. His works have been exhibited in the California Palace of the Legion of Honor, the Oakland Art Gallery, and the San Francisco Museum. Due to failing health in the late 1950s, Carlton switched from sculpture to painting.
Brents Carlton died September 6, 1962 in San Francisco.
Scope and Content Note
The Brents Carlton papers span the years 1921 to 1987 and measure 2.0 linear feet. They consist of biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, notes, a scrapbook, exhibition files, art work, photographs, and printed material that document his career as a sculptor.
Biographical materials include several autobiographical accounts, school-related materials, a student card from the Art Students' League, and other identification cards. Correspondence consists primarily of letters from family members and colleagues, including letters from Victor Arnautoff, H. Mallette Dean, Margaret De Patta, Eugen Neuhaus, Dale Nichols, and Judson T. Smith.
Personal business records include bank passbooks, pharmacy licensing records, receipts, income tax records, and ledgers of income, expenses, and art work sold. The papers also contain notes, an address book, notebooks, meeting minutes, exhibition files, a scrapbook, sketches and prints by Carlton, and numerous photographs of Carlton's works of art.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into nine series according to material type. Material within each series is arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1921-1944 (Box 1; 4 folders; reel 5873)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1922-1987, undated (Box 1, 3; 23 folders; reel 5873)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1924-1959, undated (Box 1;18 folders; reel 5873)
Series 4: Notes, 1931, undated (Box 1, 3; 5 folders; reel 5873)
Series 5: Scrapbook, 1928-1962 (Box 3; 0.1 linear feet; reel 5873)
Series 6: Exhibition Files, 1927-1983, undated (Box 1, OV 5; 16 folder; reel 5873)
Series 7: Art Work, 1924-1941, undated (Box 1, 3, OV 5; 7 folders; reel 5873)
Series 8: Photographs, 1923-1952, undated (Boxes 1-4; 36 folders; reel 5873-5874)
Series 9: Printed Material, 1923-1979, undated (Box 2; 17 folders; reel 5874)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Names" when they are creators or contributors and under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents.
Subjects-Topical:
Sculptors -- California
Types of Materials:
Photographs
Names:
Smith, Judson, 1880-1962; De Patta, Margaret, 1903-1964; Arnautoff, Victor Michail, 1896-1979; Neuhaus, Eugen, 1879-1963; Nichols, Dale, 1904-; Dean, Mallette, 1907-
Provenance
The Brents Carlton papers were donated by the artist's daughter Carrie Carlton Helser to the Archives of American Art in 1991.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is microfilmed on reels 5873-5874 and is available for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1921-1944, Series 1:; (Box 1; 4 folders; reel 5873)
  Biographical material consists of several autobiographical accounts, school-related material and miscellaneous identification cards.
  - Autobiographical Accounts, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - School-Related Material, 1921-1938, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Driver's License; Selective Service Cards, 1924-1944 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
- Correspondence, 1922-1987, undated, Series 2:; (Box 1, 3; 23 folders; reel 5873)
  Correspondence consists primarily of letters and greeting cards from family members and at least one letter each from colleagues including Victor Arnautoff, Margaret De Patta, Eugen Neuhaus, and Judson T. Smith. Letters are also found in the scrapbook filed in Series 5.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1925 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, Jan-Sep 1926 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1926 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, Nov-Dec 1926 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, Jan-Aug 1927 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, Sep-Dec 1927 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence (See Also Box 3), 1928-1929 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Oversize Christmas card, 1929 (Box 3, Reel 5873)
- Personal Business Records, 1924-1959, undated, Series 3:; (Box 1;18 folders; reel 5873)
  Personal business records consist of bank passbooks, pharmacy licensing records, ledgers of income and expenses, a ledger of art work sold, receipts for school, art sales, shipping, rent, utilities, and supplies, and income tax records.
  - Savings Account Passbooks, 1924-1930, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Pharmacy Licensing Records, 1926-1939 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Ledgers of Income and Expenses, 1925-1937, (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Ledger of Art Work Sold and Prices, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Receipts for California School of Fine Arts, 1924-1954 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Receipts for Art Sales, 1936-1944, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Receipts for the Shipping of Sculpture, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Receipts for Photography, 1936-1959 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Receipts for Room Rent (domicile), 1924 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Receipts for Studio Rent, 1931-1940, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Receipts for Studio Telephone, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Receipts for Art Supplies, 1931-1951 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1928-1943 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Income Tax Records, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
- Notes, 1931, undated, Series 4:; (Box 1, 3; 5 folders; reel 5873)
  Notes consist of an address book, notebooks recording friends' names and art media, minutes of meetings, and miscellaneous notes.
  - Address Book, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Notebook Listing Names of Friends, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Notebook Concerning Art Media, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1931, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Oversize Miscellaneous Note, undated (Box 3 (sol), Reel 5873)
- Scrapbook, 1928-1962, Series 5:; (Box 3; 0.1 linear feet; reel 5873)
  The scrapbook contains clippings, including Carlton's obituary, an exhibition catalog, and 14 letters from colleagues including Eugen Neuhaus and Dale Nichols.
  - Scrapbook containing Clippings, an Exhibition Catalog, and Letters, 1928-1962 (Box 3 (sol), Reel 5873)
- Exhibition Files, 1927-1983, undated, Series 6:; (Box 1, OV 5; 16 folders; reel 5873)
  Letters, notes, receipts, photographs, and printed material relating to Carlton's participation in exhibitions at art organizations and galleries.
  - San Francisco Art Association, 1927-1955 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - California Palace of the Legion of Honor, 1929-1983 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - The Art Center Gallery, 1930-1950, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Foundation of Western Art, 1935-1938 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1935-1983 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Amberg-Hirth Gallery, 1936-1954 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Oakland Art Gallery, 1936-1973 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Sacramento Junior College Solo Exhibition, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Golden Gate International Exposition (See Also OV 5), 1937-1940, (5 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Architectural League of New York, 1938 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - First California Ceramic Exhibition, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - National Sculpture Society Festival, 1940-1983 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Oversize Blueprint for Sculpture on California State Building, circa 1938 (Box OV 5, Reel 5873)
- Art Work, 1924-1941, undated, Series 7:; (Box 1, 3, OV 5; 7 folders; reel 5873)
  Art work by Carlton consists of 2 sketchbooks, drawings, prints, a tempera sketch, and Christmas cards. Art work by others includes woodcuts by H. Mallette Dean and a portrait drawing of Carlton by Victor Arnautoff.
  - Annotated Sketchbook, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Sketchbook, 1924-1925 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Drawings (See Also Box 3), undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Prints, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Tempera Sketch, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Christmas Cards Created by Carlton, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Art work by Others (See Also OV 5), 1928-1941, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Oversize Drawings, undated (Box 3 (sol), Reel 5873)
  - Oversize Portrait Drawing of Carlton by Victor Arnautoff, 1931 (Box OV 5, Reel 5873)
- Photographs, 1923-1952, undated, Series 8:; (Box 1-4; 36 folders; reels 5873-5874)
  Photographs are of Carlton, his family, friends, colleagues, studios, classrooms, and art work. There are also photographs of art work by others including Victor Arnautoff and Margaret De Patta.
  - Photographs of Carlton and Family Members, 1923-1952, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Carlton with Friends and Colleagues including Victor Arnautoff, 1927-1941, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Ney Street home, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Montgomery Street Studio, undated (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Polk Street Studio, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Liberty Street Apartment, 1945-1948 (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Art Classroom, 1927, (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Sculpture (See Also Box 4), 1927-1944, undated, (14 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Drawings and Paintings (See Also Box 4), 1932, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Designs by Margaret De Patta, 1932, undated (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5873)
  - Photographs of Art work by Others including Victor Arnautoff, 1927, undated (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5874)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5874)
  - Photograph Album of Carlton's Art Work, undated (Box 3 (sol), Reel 5874)
  - Oversize Photographs of Sculpture, 1927-1944, undated (Box 4 (sol), Reel 5874)
  - Oversize Photographs of a Painting, undated (Box 4 (sol), Reel 5874)
- Printed Material, 1923-1979, undated, Series 9:; (Box 2; 17 folders; reel 5874)
  Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition catalogs, brochures, and miscellaneous printed items.
  - Clippings, 1926-1979, undated, (9 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5874)
  - Exhibition Catalogs for Carlton, 1930-1951, (3 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5874)
  - Exhibition Catalogs for Others, 1949, undated (Box 2, Reel 5874)
  - Brochures for the California School of Fine Arts, 1923-1942, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5874)
  - Brochure for the Art Students' League, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Reel 5874)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1964, undated (Box 2, Reel 5874)